<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Foole upon foole, or, Six sortes of sottes. A flat foole, a leane foole, a merry foole, [brace] and [brace] a fatt foole, a cleane foole, a verrie foole. Shewing their liues, humours and behauiours, with their want of wit in their shew of wisdome. Not so strange as true.</title>
            <author>Armin, Robert, fl. 1610.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01234</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 772.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124178</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633076</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173897</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01234)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173897)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2107:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Foole upon foole, or, Six sortes of sottes. A flat foole, a leane foole, a merry foole, [brace] and [brace] a fatt foole, a cleane foole, a verrie foole. Shewing their liues, humours and behauiours, with their want of wit in their shew of wisdome. Not so strange as true.</title>
                  <author>Armin, Robert, fl. 1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Ferbrand, dwelling in Popes-head Allie neare the Royall Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Robert Armin by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Printer's device on t.p. (McK. 188β); headpiece, tailpiece, initial.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, faded and with print bleed-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
                  <note>A flat foole -- A leane foole -- A merry foole -- A fat foole -- A cleane foole -- A very foole.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fools and jesters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173897:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173897:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FOOLE VPON FOOLE, OR, Sixe ſortes of Sottes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>A flat Foole, and A fatt Foole,</item>
               <item>A leane Foole, and A cleane Foole,</item>
               <item>A merry Foole, and A verrie Foole.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Shewing their liues, humours, and behauiours, with their want of witte in their ſhew of wiſedome. Not ſo ſtrange as true.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Omnia ſunt ſex.</l>
               <l>Clonnico del mondo Snuffe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON</p>
            <p>Printed for William Ferbrand, dwelling in Popes-head Allie neare the Royall Exchange. 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:173897:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER as much health as to my ſelfe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Weete Signior, I ſalute thee kindly, how vnkindly ſo euer you ſalute my labour; deſiring thy loue, not thy dislyke: Mee thinkes it were of all thinges more then strange, that men lyuing, ſhould liue grieuing, and one to repine at an others proſperitie: it may be thou wilt wonder that I doe well; yet I wonder not that thou thinkeſt ill: for the common courſe is ſuch, the more is the pittie. What, iſt a new Booke ſayes one? I, ſayes another; tis call'd <hi>Foole vpon Foole:</hi> Nay like enough (ſayes the firſt) Fooles write as their witte workes. Why, do we not know that ſometimes the ayre purgeth with vncomfortable ſleete, as profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table raine? Are all Wits euer proſperous? no, times are leaden, dull: Age weakens, and Wits muſt needes decline. Euery one then ſaue one, and do what a can, not what a would: But I am tedious to thee and to my ſelfe: bid my Booke welcome, it may be I may liue to make thee amendes: if not, no more but this; ſuch a one dy'de in thy debt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Adew, and read true.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:173897:2"/>
            <head>How Iacke Oates playde at Cardes all alone.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Acke Oates</hi> ſitting at Cardes all alone, was dealing to himſelfe at Vide-ruſfe (for that was the game he ioyed in) and as he ſpide a Knaue: Ah knaue art there, quoth hee? When he ſpide a King, King by your leaue, quoth he: if he ſpied a Queene Queene <hi>Richard</hi> art come, quoth he? and would kneele downe and bid God bleſſe her Maieſtie (meaning indeed the then Queene, whom he heard <hi>Sir William Hollis</hi> his Maiſter ſo much to pray for:) But heere is the Ieſt, <hi>Iacke</hi> as I ſay, being at Cardes all alone, ſpying a Knaue and ſaying, Ah Knaue art there? A ſimple Seruingman being in the Hall waighting his maiſters comming, walking by, and hearing him ſay ſo, thought he had cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him Knaue, tooke the matter in dudgin, and miſcalled the Foole: another Seruingman more fooliſh then both, tooke <hi>Iackes</hi> part, ſo that in ſhort time they two fell together by the eares; who being parted, <hi>Iacke Oates</hi> giues them each one a Knaue, and ſo takes them into the Buttry to drinke: the Knight comes in, ſeeing the Hall not yet quiet, aſkt the matter? <hi>Iacke</hi> comes, Ile tell thee <hi>Willy,</hi> quoth hee: As I was a playing at Cardes, one ſeeing I wonne all I playde for, would needes haue the Knaue from mee; which as very a Knaue is hee ſeeing, would needes beare him Knaue for company: ſo to bid them both wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to thy houſe, I haue bin to intreat the Knaue thy Butler to make them drinke. I ſayes Sir <hi>William,</hi> and you like a Knaue made them fall out. I anſwered <hi>Iacke,</hi> and your drinke Sir knaue made them friendes. Sir <hi>William</hi> laughing, departed.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:3"/>
               <head>How Iacke hit a Noble-man a boxe on the eare.</head>
               <p>Newes came to Sir <hi>William</hi> that ſuch a Nobleman was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to his houſe, great prouiſion was made for his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: and amongſt all <hi>Iacke Oates</hi> put on his now Motley coate, a cleane Muckender, and his new ſhooes. Much preparation was made, which were too long to tell, for Ile aſſure ye it was one of the greateſt Earles in England, vnfit to name here: but the Knight and his Ladie met him at the gate to entertaine him: Sir <hi>William</hi> with a low congy ſaluted him, the good Ladie, as is the Courtly cuſtom, was kiſt of this Noble man: <hi>Iacke Oates</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him kiſſe his Lady, on the ſodaine giues the Earle a ſound boxe on the eare: knaue (quoth he) kiſſe Sir <hi>Willies</hi> wife? the good Knight amazed at this, cauſed him to be whipt: but the kinde No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man knowing ſimplicitie the ground of his errour, would not ſuffer it, but putting it vp, left him and entred the houſe. <hi>Iacke</hi> ſeeing they were ſad, and he had done amiſſe, had this wit in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie to ſhaddowe it: he comes after and aſkt the Earle where his hand was? Here (quoth hee) with that he ſhakes him by it, and ſayes, I miſtooke it before, knowing not your eare from your hand being ſo like one another: <hi>Iacke</hi> thought hee had mended the matter, but now he was whipt indeede, and had his payment alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Thus fooles thinking to bee wiſe, become flat fooliſh, but all is one, <hi>Iacke</hi> neuer repented him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How a Minſtrell became a foole artificiall, and had <hi>Iacke Oates</hi> his reward for his labour.</head>
               <p>AT a Chriſtmas time, when great logs furniſh the Hall fire: when Brawne is in ſeaſon, &amp; in deede all Reueling is regarded: this gallant knight kept open houſe for all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, where Beefe, Beere, and Bread was no niggard. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the pleaſures prouided, a Noyſe of Minſtrelles, and a Lincolnſhire Bagpipe was prepared: the Minſtrels for the great Ceamber, the Bagpipe for the Hall: the Minſtrels to ſerue vp the Knights meate, and the Bagpipe for the common dauncing.
<pb facs="tcp:173897:3"/>
                  <hi>Iacke</hi> could not endure to be in the common Hall, for indeede the foole was a little proude minded, and therefore was altogether in the great Chamber at my Ladies or Sir <hi>Williams</hi> elbo one time being very melancholy, the Knight to rouſe him vp, ſaide, hence foole hence, Ile haue another foole, thou ſhalt dwell no longer with me: <hi>Iack</hi> to this anſwered little, though indeed ye could not anger him worſe: A Gentleman at the boord anſweres, if it pleaſe you ſir Ile bring ye another foole ſoone: I pray ye do (quoth the knight) and he ſhall be welcome. <hi>Iacke</hi> fell a crying, and departed mad and angry downe into the great Hall: and being ſtrong armed (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I deſcribed him, caught the Bagpipes from the piper, knocke them about his pate, that he laid the fellow for dead on the ground, and all broken, carries the pipes vp into the great Chamber, and layes them on the fire. The Knigt knowing by <hi>Iacke,</hi> that ſome thing was amiſſe, ſends downe to ſee: newes of this ieſt came, the knight angry (but to no purpoſe, for he loued the foole aboue all, &amp; that the houſhold knew, elſe <hi>Iacke</hi> had paide for it, for the common peoples dauncing was ſpoiled) ſent downe <hi>Iacke,</hi> and had him out of his ſight: <hi>Iacke</hi> cryes hang ſir <hi>Willy,</hi> hang ſir <hi>Willy</hi> &amp; departes.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>William</hi> not knowing how to amend the matter, cauſed the Piper to be caried to bed, who was very ill: and ſaid I would now giue a gold noble for a foole indeede to anger him throughly: one of the Minſtrels whiſpered a Gentleman in the eare, and ſayd, if it pleaſed him he would, whereat the Gentleman laught: the Knight demaunded the reaſon of his laughing, I pray you tell mee (quoth he) for laughing could neuer come in a better time, the foole hath madded me. If it pleaſe you (ſayes the Gentleman) here is a good fellow will goe and attire him in one of his coates, and can in all pointes behaue himſelfe naturally like ſuch a one: it is good (ſayes the Knight) and I prethee good fellow about it, &amp; one go cal <hi>Iack Oates</hi> hither, that we may hold him with talke in the meane time.</p>
               <p>The ſimple Minſtrill thinking to worke wonders, as one ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed at the good oportunitie threw his Fiddle one way, his ſtick another, and his caſe the third way, and was in ſuch a caſe of ioye, that it was no boote to bid him make haſt, but proud of the knights fauour away he flings, as if he went to take poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome great Lordſhip, but where ere he got by it, I am ſure his fiddle with the fall fell a peeces, which grieued his maiſter ſo that in loue and pitie
<pb facs="tcp:173897:4"/>
he laughed till the water ran downe his cheekes: beſide this good Knight was lik to keepe a bad Chriſtmas, for the Bagpipes &amp; the Muſique went to wracke, the one burnt, and the other broken.</p>
               <p>In comes <hi>Iacke Oates,</hi> and (being merry) told the Knight and the reſt, that a Country-wench in the Hall had eaten Garlicke, and there was ſeuenteene men poyſoned with kiſſing her: for it was vſe to ieſt thus: by &amp; by comes in a meſſenger (one of the Knights men) to tell him that ſuch a Gentleman had ſent his Foole to dwell with him. He is welcome ſayes the Knight, for I am weary of this Foole, goe bid him come in, <hi>Iacke</hi> bid him welcome: they all laught to ſee <hi>Iackes</hi> cullour come and goe, like a wiſe man ready to make a good end: What ſay you to this, ſayes the Knight? not one word ſayes <hi>Iacke.</hi> They cinged with a knife at the bottome of a glaſſe, as toulling the bell for the Foole, who was ſpeechleſſe and would die (then which, nothing could more anger him:) but now the thought of the new come Foole ſo much mooued him, that hee was as dead as a doore nayle: ſtanding on tip-toe looking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the doore to behold his arriuall, that he would put his noſe out of ioynt.</p>
               <p>By and by enters my artificiall Foole in his old cloathes, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wry mouthes, dauncing, looking a ſquint: who when <hi>Iacke</hi> beheld, ſodainly he flew at him, and ſo violently beate him, that all the Table roſe, but could ſcarce get him off: well, off he was at length, the Knight cauſed the broken ones to be by themſelues. My poore Minſtrill with a fall had his head broake to the ſkull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ground, his face ſcratcht, that which was worſt of all, his left eye put out, and withall ſo ſore bruzed, that he could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtand nor goe: the Knight cauſed him to be laide with the Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, who was alſo hurt in the like conflict, who lackt no good loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to, becauſe they miſcarried in the Knights ſeruice: but euer after <hi>Iacke Oates</hi> could not endure to heare any talke of another Foole to be there, and the Knight durſt not make ſuch a motion. The Piper and the Minſtrill being in bed together, one cryed, O his backe and face the other, O his face and eye: the one cryed O his Pipe, the other, O his Fiddle. Good Muſicke or broken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts they agree well together: but when they were well, they were contented for their paines: they had both money and the Knights fauour. Here you haue heard the difference twixt a Flat
<pb facs="tcp:173897:4"/>
foole naturall, and a Flat foole artificiall, one that had his kinde, and the other who fooliſhly followed his owne minde: on which two is written this Rime.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Naturall Fooles, are prone to ſelfe conceite:</l>
                  <l>Fooles artificiall, with their wits lay waite</l>
                  <l>To make themſelues fooles, likeing the diſguyes,</l>
                  <l>To feede their owne mindes, and the gazers eyes.</l>
                  <l>Hee that attempts daunger, and is free,</l>
                  <l>Hurting himſelfe, being well cannot ſee:</l>
                  <l>Muſt with the Fidler heere weare the Fooles coates,</l>
                  <l>And bide his pennance ſign'd him by Iacke Oates.</l>
                  <l>All ſuch ſay I, that vſe flat foolerie,</l>
                  <l>Beare this, beare more; this flat Fooles companie.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How <hi>Iacke Oates</hi> eate vp a Quince Pye, being of choyſe prouided for Sir <hi>William.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IAcke Oates</hi> could neuer abide the Cooke, by reaſon that hee would ſcald him out of the Kitchin. Vpon a time he had a great charge from his Lady to make her a Quince Pie of purpoſe for Sir <hi>Williams</hi> owne eating, which the Cooke endeuored to do, and ſent to <hi>Lincolne</hi> of purpoſe to the Apothecaries for choyſe Quinces: <hi>Iacke</hi> being at this charge giuen, thought to be euen with the Cooke, and waited the time when this Pie was made: it hapned ſo the Cooke could get no Quinces, my Lady (for it was the Knights deſire to haue one) ſent about to <hi>Boſton,</hi> and all the chiefe townes, but al in vaine, the ſeaſon ſerued not: but rather then ſir <hi>William</hi> ſhould be vnfurniſhed, ſent to <hi>Lincolne</hi> againe to buy vp many Quinces ready preſerued at Pothecaries, which ſhe had, though with great coſt. The Knight aſking his Lady for his Pie, ſhe told him with much adoe ſhe had preuailed, but with no little paines in ſeeking Quinces, for ſhe was faine to buy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ready pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, &amp; to make a vertue of neceſſity that way. Sir <hi>William</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was ſo, ſayd it ſhould be as well eaten, &amp; ſent for his friends, Gentlemen, and others of no ſmall account. There was other great cheare prouided to furniſh vp this ſumptuous Feaſt, and as he inuited them, he told them it was a Quince Pie, which he would haue eaten: the day drew on, and the Gentles were come, and all was in a redines, &amp; ſtill <hi>Iacke</hi> forgat not the Pie, but ſtood faintly
<pb facs="tcp:173897:5"/>
ſicke, and refuſed his meate: the Knight ſory that his beſt diſh fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, made no ſmall accompt of his welfare, aſkt him: <hi>Iacke,</hi> ſayes hee, Where lyes thy paine? In my mouth ſayes hee (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in deede his mouth hung for the Quince Pie:) a Barber was ſent for from a Market towne hard by, who ſearcht his mouth and could find no cauſe of paine: but ſir <hi>William</hi> thinking the Foole wanted wit to tell his griefe (though not wit to play the cheefe) bade the Barber depart, aſking <hi>Iacke</hi> what he would eate? He ſayd nothing: What he would drinke? He ſayd nothing: which made ſir <hi>William</hi> doubt much of his health, refuſing his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, when it was vſually his practiſe, and the Knight ioyed in it too: aſkt him if he would walke? he ſayd no: if he would lie downe? ſtill anſwering no; but would ſtande by the Kitchin fire. The Knight that knew he neuer came there but he did ſome exployte, forgetting that, led him by the hand (ſo much he made of him) and bad the Cooke ſee he wanted nothing. <hi>Iacke</hi> ſtanding ſtil, groand &amp; ſayd: If he dyed, he would forgiue all the world but the Cooke. Hang Foole (ſayes the Cooke) I care not for thee, die to morrow if thou wilt, and ſo followed his buſines. They knockt to the Dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, &amp; the dinner went vp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Iacke</hi> had a ſheepes eye in the Ouen: anone the ſecond courſe came, the Pie was drawne, ſet by, and among other backt meates was to be ſent vp, but wanting Suger, ſtept aſide to the ſpicerie to fetch it, and <hi>Iacke</hi> in the meane time catcheth the Pie and claps it vnder his coate, &amp; ſo runnes through the Hall into the Yard, where was a broad Moate, and as he ran, the hot Pie burnd his belly: I ſayes <hi>Iacke,</hi> are yee ſo hot Sir <hi>Willies</hi> Pie, Ile quence ye anone ſir <hi>Willies</hi> Pie ſayes he, and ſtraight very ſubtilly leapes into the Moate vp to the arme-pits, and there ſtood eating the Pie. The Cooke comes in, miſſes the Pie, withall miſſes <hi>Iacke,</hi> cryes out, the Pie: ſir <hi>Williams</hi> Pie was gone, the Author of that feaſt was gone, and they all were vndone: a hurly burly went through the houſe, and one comes and whiſpers the Lady with the newes: ſhee tels ſir <hi>William</hi> how <hi>Iacke Oates</hi> had ſtolen the Pie. <hi>Iacke</hi> was ſearcht for, and anone found in the Moate. It was told the Knight where the Foole was eating it: Gentlemen (quoth he) we are disfurniſhed of our feaſt, for <hi>Iacke</hi> my Foole is in my Moate vp to the arme-pits eating of the Pie. They laught and ran to the Windows to ſee the ieſt:
<pb facs="tcp:173897:5"/>
there they might ſee <hi>Iacke</hi> eate, the Cooke call, the people hallow, but to no purpoſe: <hi>Iacke</hi> fed, and feeding greedily (more to anger the Cooke, then diſapoint ſir <hi>William</hi>) euer as he burnt his mouth with haſte, dipt the Pye in the water to coole it: O ſayes the Cook it is Sir <hi>Williams</hi> owne Pye ſirra: O ſaies <hi>Iacke</hi> hang thee and ſir <hi>Willy</hi> too I care not, it is mine now: ſaue Sir <hi>William</hi> ſome ſayes one, ſaue my Lady ſome ſaies another: by <hi>Iames</hi> not a bit ſayes <hi>Iacke,</hi> and eate vp all, to the wonder of the beholders, who neuer knew him eate ſo much before, but drinke ten times more: at length out comes <hi>Iacke</hi> dropping drye, and goes to get fire to dry him: the knight and the reſt all laught a good at the ieſt, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to mend it. Sir <hi>William</hi> ſends for the Cooke, who came vp with a ſorrowfull hart, &amp; lamentably complaining, ſaid: it was the Knights fault for placing him in the Kitchin, where hee neuer was, but he did the like villany. The Knight not ſatiſfied with the Cookes anſwere, preſently diſcharges him of his ſeruice, and ſent him to liue elſewhere: go ſayes he, truſſe vp your trinkets and bee gone: the Cooke ſeeing no remedy departed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iack</hi> being dry vp he comes, and knowing he had offended, tels a ieſt (for it was the maner ſo to do) how a yong man brake his cod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peece poynt and let all be ſeene that God ſent him, or ſuch foole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but that was not enough, and to chide him, was to make worſe of things then twas, and to no purpoſe neither. Sir <hi>William</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded why he eate the Pye? becauſe I had a ſtomacke ſayes <hi>Iacke:</hi> would nought elſe ſerue, ſayes the Knight but my Pye? O no <hi>Willy,</hi> ſaies he, thou would not be angry then, and the Cooke had not beene turned away: but all is well, thou art rich enough to buy more. The Knight perceiuing the fooles enuy, ſent for the Cooke, and did let him enioy his place againe. So all parties well pleaſed, but the yong big-bellied women, who perchance longed for this long looked for Pye, but if they did, though long looke for comes at laſt, yet they ſhoote ſhort that ayme to hit this marke, for <hi>Iacke Oates</hi> had eaten the Pye and ſerued himſelfe. This was a flat foole, yet now and then a blinde man may hit a Crow, and you know a fooles boult is ſoone ſhot: out it goes hoppen how it will: had <hi>Iacke</hi> kept his owne counſell the Cooke had beene ſtill out of ſeruice, and had beene reuenged, but now being in his place againe may liue to crye quittance for the Quince Pye.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <head>A Fat Foole</head>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:6"/>
               <head>The Deſcription of Iemy Camber, <hi>A Fat Foole Naturall.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THis Fat foole was a Scot borne, brought vp,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Sterlin,</hi> twentie miles fram <hi>Edinborough:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who being but young, was for the King caught vp:</l>
                  <l>Seru'd this Kings Father all his life time through.</l>
                  <l>A yarde high and a nayle no more his ſtature,</l>
                  <l>Smooth fac't fayre ſpoken, yet vnkinde by nature.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Two yardes in compaſſe and a nayle I reede</l>
                  <l>Was he at forty yeeres, ſince when I heard not,</l>
                  <l>Nor of his life or death, and further heede,</l>
                  <l>Since I neuer read, I looke not, nor regard not,</l>
                  <l>But what at that time <hi>Iemy Camber</hi> was,</l>
                  <l>As I haue heard Ile write, and ſo let paſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His head was ſmall, his hayre long on the ſame,</l>
                  <l>One eare was bigger then the other farre:</l>
                  <l>His fore-head full, his eyes ſhinde like a flame,</l>
                  <l>His noſe flat and his beard ſmall, yet grew ſquare.</l>
                  <l>His lips but little, and his wit was leſſe,</l>
                  <l>But wide of mouth, few teeth I muſt confeſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His middle thicke, as I haue ſaid before,</l>
                  <l>Indifferent thighes and knees, but very ſhort:</l>
                  <l>His legges be ſquare, a foote long and no more,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe very preſence made the King much ſport.</l>
                  <l>And a pearle ſpoone he ſtill wore in his cap,</l>
                  <l>To eate his meate he lou'd, and got by hap</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A pretty little foote, but a big hand,</l>
                  <l>On which he euer wore rings rich and good:</l>
                  <l>Backward well made as any in that land,</l>
                  <l>Though thicke, and he did come of gentle bloud.</l>
                  <l>But of his wiſedome ye ſhall quickly heare,</l>
                  <l>How this Fat Foole was made on euery where.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:6"/>
               <head>How Iemy Camber this Fat Foole, gaue his Chayne of Golde from his necke to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant his life.</head>
               <p>WHen the King and Nobles of Scotland had welcomed <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Camber</hi> to the Court, who was their Countrey-man borne in <hi>Sterlin,</hi> but twentie miles from <hi>Edinborough,</hi> this Kings birth towne, as <hi>Greenewich</hi> was our late Queenes. They reaſoned with him to vnderſtand his wit, which indeed was iuſt none at all, yet merry and pleaſing, wherat the King reioiced: and ſeeing he was ſo fat, cauſed his Doctors and Phiſitians to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to him, but Phiſicke could not alter nature, and hee would neuer be but a S. Vincents Turnip, thicke and round. Wherefore the Doctors perſwaded his grace, that the purging of the Sea was good for him: well, nothing was vndone, that might bee done to make <hi>Iemy Camber</hi> a tal little ſlender man. When yet he lookt like a Norfolke dumpling, thicke and ſhort. Well to Leeth was he ſent, which is the harbour towne of ſuch ſhippes as arriue at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinborough:</hi> neere they cannot come, which is ſome myle from the Cittie. To Sea they put in a ſhip, at whoſe departure they diſcharged Ordinance, as one that departed from the land with the Kings fauour: the Earle Huntley was ſent with him to Sea, to accompanie him, ſo high he was eſteemed with the King. Who hearing the Ordinance goe off, would aſke what they doe now? Marry ſayes the Earle, they ſhoot at our enemies: O ſaies he, hit I pray God. Againe they diſcharge, what doe they now quoth he? marry now the enemie ſhootes at vs. O miſſe I pray God (ſaies <hi>Iemy Camber:</hi>) ſo euer after it was a ieſt in the Scottiſh Court hit or miſſe quoth <hi>Iemy Camber:</hi> that if a maide had a barne, and did pennance at the Croſſe in the high Towne of <hi>Edinborough:</hi> what hath ſhe done? did ſhe hit or miſſe? ſhe hath hit ſaies the other, better ſhe had miſt ſayes the firſt: and ſo long time after this ieſt was in memorie, yea I haue heard it my ſelf, &amp; ſome will talke of it at this day. Wel to ſea they put on a fair ſunſhine day, where <hi>Iemy</hi> ſtood fearefull of euery calme billow, where it was no boote to bid him tel what the ſhip was made of, for he did it deuoutly: but ſee the chaunce, a ſodaine flaw or guſt roſe, the winds held ſtrong Eaſt and by weſt, and the ſhip was in great daunger, inſomuch as the Earle,
<pb facs="tcp:173897:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173897:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173897:8"/>
Maiſter, and all began to feare the weather: by &amp; by a ſtronger gale blew &amp; ſplit their maine Maſt, &amp; gaue their ſhip a mighty leake, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as the cracke made them all ſcreeke out: which <hi>Iemy</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring was almoſt dead with feare: ſome fell to pumping, others on their knees to praying. But the Fat foole ſeeing themſelues in this danger, thought there was no way but one with them, &amp; was halfe dead with feare, in the end the winde turned, and the raging of the Sea began to ceaſe: I warrant thee now (quoth the Maiſter) <hi>Iemy</hi> we ſhall not be drowned: I, will ye warrant vs, ſaies the foole? I, ſayes the Maiſter, Ile giue thee my ſhip for thy chayne if wee bee drowned: beare witnes my Lord ſaies he, a plaine bargaine, and with that threw the Maiſter his chaine, who would haue giuen it to the Earle, but ioy of their ſcape made him delight in the ieſt, and therefore the Maiſter enioyed his bargaine: With much adoe they attained thither againe, where the King fearefull before, awayted their landing now, and ſeeing <hi>Iemy</hi> not a iot leſſe of body then hee was, (onely lightened of his chaine) how now, quoth he, how doeſt thou man? O ſayes <hi>Iemy,</hi> well now King, but ill had not the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter beene, who warranted our liues for my chaine, the beſt bargain that euer I made, for no way could I haue bene a looſer: how, ſaies the King? marry Ile tel thee King, quoth he, ſay we had bin drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, his ſhip was forfeit to me for my chayne, Earle Huntley was a witneſſe to the bargaine: and now wee are not drowned, for my chayne did warrant our liues of the Maiſter: nay, ſayes the Earle, not our liues, none but yours <hi>Iemy:</hi> our liues were as ſafe vnwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted without a chaine. With this the foole had ſome feeling of ſence and on the ſodaine cried out mainely for his chayne againe, which was reſtored to him by the Maiſter, but he loſt nothing by that, for he attained to a ſuit, as the ſtory ſayes, that he had beene three yeres aboue. Thus the King &amp; Nobles went to <hi>Edinborough</hi> merrily talking of their feare and welfare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How Iemy Camber gaue fiue French Crownes for a Sallet of an atchiſon price, which in our money was three farthings.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IEmy</hi> this Fat foole vſed euery day to go from the Abbey in the low towne, vp the hill into the Citie of <hi>Edinborough,</hi> and one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening aboue the reſt, he met with a broken Virgine, one that had had a barne (as there they are knowne by their attire) wearing a
<pb facs="tcp:173897:8"/>
looſe kerchiffe hanging downe backward, ſhe I ſay cryed Sallets as thus: buy any <hi>Cibus Salletea. Iemy</hi> deſirous of Sallets, calles her to him: laſſe ſayes he, what ſhall I giue thee for a good Sallet? fayre ſir ſayes the wench (for ſhe knew him for the Kinges foole, &amp; ſhe could not pleaſe him better then to call him fayre ſir) you muſt giue mee an atchiſon: nowe hee hauing nothing but ſixe French Crownes about him, canſt thou change mee a Crowne ſayes hee? yea ſir ſayes ſhe: he giues her a French Crowne, and ſhe gaue him a Sallet for it, and ſhe went her way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iemy</hi> thinkes it was mutch to giue a crowne for that, for which ſhe did demaund but an atchiſon: which in our money is but three farthinges, he runnes after and ſayes, ſhe had his fayreſt crowne, but ſaies he giue mee that and take your choyſe of theſe: thinking by that deuiſe to get the firſt Crowne againe. Will ye chaunge ſayes the laſſe? I ſayes the foole: ſo ſhe takes all the fiue and giues him one againe, &amp; ſo laughing at his folly, goes her way, it was in vaine to exclayme, for they will hold faſt what they get: but my fat foole goes home to eate his Sallet, &amp; inuites the King to a deere diſh, and made him laugh hartely at the ieſt: The King calles for Viniger to his Sallet, becauſe his ſweete meate ſhould haue ſower ſauce, &amp; perſwaded him it was well bought, otherwiſe if the foole had repented his bargaine, it was his manner to cry for his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney againe, and without it all the Court could not quiet him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How <hi>Iemy</hi> this fat Foole, ſwet almoſt to death, and neuer knew the reaſon.</head>
               <p>BEtwixt <hi>Edenborough</hi> Abbey the Kings place and <hi>Leeth,</hi> there ſtands an euen plaine greene Meddow, in which the King vſed moſt of his ſports: amongſt which he rode thither one day to run at the Gloue, or the King, as his Grace ſhould pleaſe. With him rides <hi>Iemy Camber</hi> on a trotting Mule: it was then a maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous hot day. O (ſayes <hi>Iemy</hi>) how cold the weather is (ſo wiſe he was that he ſcarce knew hot from cold.) No ſayes the King, it is hot, looke how I ſweat. No, ſayes <hi>Iemy</hi> the Sunne blowes very cold. No, ſayes the King, the windes ſhines very hot. The Foole was almoſt angry to be croſſed, &amp; ſaid, he would be hanged at night if he did ſweate that day: with this merry talke they rode on: but one of the Kinges Footemen hearing this, told the King at their
<pb facs="tcp:173897:9"/>
returne he would make his Grace laugh hartely: ſo the King very gallantly ran that time, &amp; neuer miſt the gloue, &amp; ſo did the Lords: which <hi>Iemy</hi> ſeeing, ſayd it was nothing to do: The King bad him run, he did ſo: but the Gloue lay ſtill, and <hi>Iemy</hi> could not do it.</p>
               <p>The Kings footman (that watcht to do him a good turne) ſaid, <hi>Iemy</hi> could do it better blindfolde: what can he q. the King, I wil neuer beleeue it? you ſhall ſee elſe quoth he: whereat <hi>Iemy</hi> maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led much, that without ſight a man could doe that which with all his might and ſight he could not do, was deſirous to make tryall, ſo was blinded with a ſcarfe, while another tooke vp the gloue, and was ready for the ieſt: <hi>Iemy</hi> runnes, ah for my Maiſter ſaies hee, they all ſhout alowd and cry rarely well done, and one vnblindes him, while another puts the gloue on the ſpeare. So ſimple hee was, that he thought it was ſtrange, and bragged all that day not a little: the King did alight and went to drinke wine at the Lord Hunnes houſe, and <hi>Iemy</hi> went with him, while the foote-man had time to worke his will, and mingling a conceit with butter (which I will not name, leaſt ſome one ſhould practiſe the like) clapt it vnder the ſaddle, and as they rode home to <hi>Edinborough,</hi> ſaies the King, what ſay you to the weather now <hi>Iemy?</hi> mee thinkes it is hotter then it was? nay it is colder ſayes he, for I begin to ſweate.</p>
               <p>The trotting of his Mule made the mingled confection lather ſo, that it got into his breeches, and workt vp to the crowne of his head, I to the ſole of his foote, and ſo he ſweat profoundly: ſtill he wipt and he wipt, ſweating more and more, they laught a good to ſee him in that taking: now you muſt be hanged, quoth the King, as your bargaine was, for you ſweat very much: what remedie, ſayes hee, I am content to be hanged, but while I liue after, Ile neuer beleeue cold weather will make one ſweat: no more will I ſayes the King, but hot weather will. Hot or cold, ſayes <hi>Iemy,</hi> I am warme now I am ſure, I would I were ouer head and eares in ſome Riuer to coole mee. So ſimple he was, that he knew not whether it was the Sunne or the wind made him ſweat: at night the King cauſed him to be waſht, and perfumed, yet he was ſcarce ſweete twentie dayes after. Thus this fatte Foole chaft, but not in his owne greaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:9"/>
               <head>How this fatte Foole <hi>Iemy Camber,</hi> ran with the Kings beſt Foote-man for a wager, and won it.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IEmy,</hi> who was as you haue heard, a tall low man, and was ſwift of foote, on a time challenged the Kings beſt Foote-man, for a wager to run with him from the Abbey vp the hill to Cannegate, (which ſtood euering to <hi>Edenborough,</hi> as Ludgate doth to Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the Kings place about Temple barre:) the King being told of this challenge, thought it would be good ſport to ſee it perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſtill perſwaded <hi>Iemy</hi> to dare his Foote-man, who before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him, and knew Fooles would talke any thing, though farre vnfit to performe any thing. Still the King would ſay hee was made nimble to runne, and aſkt euery Noblemans iudgement, who likewiſe ſoothed the King: it was ſo that they made him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue he was ſwift of foote, that I thinke <hi>Iemy</hi> in the end perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himſelfe, that none but fatt men could run well, and nimble men being light, would fall ſooneſt, conſidering that light things being of ſmall ſubſtannce, not feeling themſelues, would ſurely fal. But heere is the ſport, the Foot-man ſeeing it was the Kings pleaſure to ſee the wager tryed, dared him, which made <hi>Iemy</hi> mad, that he would runne with him from <hi>Edenborough</hi> to <hi>Barwicke</hi> (which was fourtie myles) in one day, as a thing vnpoſſible as to pull downe a Church in one houer, and to builde it againe in an other: for <hi>Iemy</hi> was loſt in the Kings company once of purpoſe, but fiue myle from the Citty, at the Earle Mortons caſtle at <hi>da Keth,</hi> and they thought he would neuer haue come home againe: when the King heard euery houre he was comming, and ſtill as he increated euery paſſenger to let him ride: by the Kinges watch in the high way, they had warning giuen to the contrary: for he was ſeuen dayes going fiue myle: then iudge how long he would be a running fourtie? you will muſe how he did for meate all the time: Ile tell you he faſted all day, and went ſupperleſſe to bed, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his firſt ſounde ſleepe, meate was brought and layde by him and a Choppin of Wine (for ſo they call it theere) which made him at his comming to court tell the King, Heauen was gentler then Earth, for earthly men would ſhew him no fauour, neither to ride nor feede him, when he was euery night caſt into a ſounde
<pb facs="tcp:173897:10"/>
ſleepe, and then when he wakt was ſure of meate from heauen to feede on: when the meate came from the Kings Kitchin at <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough</hi> Abbey.</p>
               <p>But to goe forward with our challenge, the King ſayd the firſt word ſhould ſtand, and on <hi>Iemyes</hi> head he layd a thouſand marks: the Lady Carmichell that laught to heare all this, wagered as much on the Footmans head: the day was appoynted the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row being Thurſday, to begin at fiue a clocke in the after noone, in the coole of the euening, and euery one to his race muſt make him ready. <hi>Iemy</hi> as he had ſeene the Kinges Footman do, waſht his feete with Beere, and ſoakt them in Butter: ſo all that night, and the next day, there was nothing but <hi>Iemy</hi> and his prouiſion to that great iourney. The time came, <hi>Iemy</hi> was ſtript into his ſhirt, truſt round for the purpoſe: the Footman and hee begins to runne: the Footman makes great ſhew of labour, and the Foole made the ſubſtaunce, for hee was quickly in a ſweat: they puft and they blowd, they ranne as ſwift as a pudding would creepe. <hi>Iemy</hi> thought himſelfe no ſmall foole to out-run the Footman, and did in his minde aſſure himſelfe to win: the King laughes to ſee the toyle he made, and the Footman made great ſhew and litle paines. By and by <hi>Iemy</hi> calles for drinke, and the King loath hee ſhould haue any harme with labour, cauſed him to haue a mixed drinke to caſt him into a ſleepe: who when he had drunke, as he ran on his wager, he dropt downe in the ſtreete, as heauy as if a leaden plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met that makes a Iacke turne the ſpitte, and fallen on the earth dab: there he ſlept, and was carryed by commaund to the top of the hill, and layde downe againe: there he ſlept halfe an houre, and when he wakt, he remembred his iourney: ſeeing people ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, vp he gets, away he iogs, and neuer lookes behind him: and ſeeing Cannegate ſo neere him, had not the witte to wonder how he came there, but layde hold on the ring of the gate, &amp; ſtayde to be ſeene. By and by the Footeman comes ſweating, with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter powred on his face and head: O my hart ſayes hee: O my legges! ſayes <hi>Iemy,</hi> I will not do ſo much for all Scotlande againe. Well, <hi>Iemy</hi> cryes victorie, victorie: and there was the Kinges Coach at hand to carry him home, for of himſelfe he could neuer haue gone, had his life laine on it. But when he came home, the bragges he made, the glory he gotte, how hee out-ranne the
<pb facs="tcp:173897:10"/>
Footeman (and ran ſo eaſily as if he had beene aſleepe) was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull: I, it was ſport enough for the King a month after to heare him tell it. Well, the King wonne the wager he thought, and that was honour ſufficient for him: not three dayes after he bad the King put away all his Footemen, and he would ſerue his turne to any place. The King thanked him for his good wil, and ſaid when his neede was great, he would make bolde to vſe him: ſo <hi>Iemy</hi> this fat foole euer bragged of this wager.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How this fat Foole Iemy was ſtung with nettles, and how after vnknowne to himſelfe, helped to make his owne graue.</head>
               <p>THere was a Laundres of the Towne, whoſe daughter vſed often to the Court, to bring home ſhirtes and bandes, which <hi>Iemy</hi> had long time loued and ſolicited, but to no ende, ſhee would not yeeld him an inch of her maidenhead: now <hi>Iemy</hi> vowed he would haue it all. Well, ſhe conſented at laſt, and to bee ſhort, ſoone at night at nine a clocke, being in the winter, when ſhe knew her mother to bee gone to watch with a ſicke bodie, he ſhould come and all that night lye with her: <hi>Iemy</hi> though witleſſe, wanted no knauiſh meaning in this, thought long till it was night. But in the afternoone, the mayde goes vp to the Caſtle, and gathers a great baſket of Nettles, and comming home, ſtrawes them vnder the bed.</p>
               <p>Night comes, nine a clocke ſtrikes, <hi>Iemy</hi> on his horſe comes riding forward, ſets him vp and knockes at the doore, ſhe lets him in, and bids him welcome bonny man: to bed hee goes, and <hi>Iemy</hi> neuer was vſed but to lye naked, for it is the vſe of a number, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which number ſhe knew <hi>Iemy</hi> was one, who no ſooner was in bed, but ſhe herſelfe knocke at the doore, and herſelfe aſked who was there, which <hi>Iemy</hi> hearing was afraid of her mother: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Sir (ſayes ſhe) creepe vnder the bed, my mother comes. <hi>Iemy</hi> buſtled not a little, vnder he creepes ſtarke naked, where hee was ſtung with Nettles: iudge you that haue feeling of ſuch matters, there he lay, turning this way and that way, here he ſtung his leg, here his ſhoulder, there his buttocks: but the mayde hauing lockt the doore to him, went to bed and there lay he in durance (as they ſay) till morning: when the day broke vp gets the maide, to Court
<pb facs="tcp:173897:11"/>
ſhe goes, and tels the Kings chamberlaine of the matter, and hee tolde the King, who laughed thereat rigt hartily.</p>
               <p>The Chamberlaine was ſent to ſee him there, who when he came, found him faſt aſleepe vnder the bed ſtarke naked, bathing in Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, whoſe ſkinne when he wakened him, was all bliſtered gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly. The Kings Chamberlaine bid him ariſe and come to the King. I will not, quoth he. I will goe make my graue. See how thinges chaunced, he ſpake truer then he was aware: for the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine going home without him, tolde the King his aunſwere. <hi>Iemy</hi> roſe, made him ready, takes his horſe and rides to the church yard, in the high towne, where he found the Sexton (as the cuſtom is there) making 9 graues, three for men, three for women, &amp; three for children, and who ſo dyes next, firſt comes firſt ſeru'd: lend mee thy ſpade, ſayes <hi>Iemy,</hi> and with that digs a hole, which hole he bids him make for his graue, and doth giue him a French crowne, the man willing to pleaſe him (more for his gold then his pleaſure) did ſo: and the foole gets vpon his horſe, and rides to a Gentleman of the towne, and on the ſodaine within two houres after dyed: of whome the Sexton telling, he was buried there indeed. Thus you ſee fooles haue a geſſe at wit ſometime, and the wiſeſt could haue done no more, nor ſo much. But thus our fat Foole fils a leaue graue with his carkaſſe, vpon which graue the King cauſed a ſtone of Marble to be put, on which the Poets did write theſe lines in remembrance of him to this day.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>He that gard all men till ieare,</l>
                  <l>Iemy a Chamber he ligges here:</l>
                  <l>Pray for his ſale, for he is geane,</l>
                  <l>And here a ligges beneath this ſteane.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <head>A Leane Foole</head>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:11"/>
               <head>How Leanard a leane Foole, playde at ſlide groate by himſelfe after dinner, when his belly was full.</head>
               <p>IN the merry Forreſt of Shearewood dwels a kinde Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whoſe name I omit, fearing I too much offend in med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with his foole: but I truſt he will pardon me, for ſithence he is ſo wel knowne there abouts, I thinke it not amiſſe to tell it at London, that people ſeeing the ſtrange workes of God, in his dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering creatures, we that haue perfect reſemblance of God, both in ſence and ſimilitude, may the btter praiſe his name, that we differ from them whoſe humors we read, ſee, &amp; heare, are not ſo ſtrange as true. I ſay againe, this Gentleman hath yet a Foole, <hi>Leanard</hi> they call him: leane of body, looking like enuie, whoſe conditions agree with his countenaunce: one time aboue all other, he lockt himſelfe into a Parlour, where all alone he playd at ſlide groate, as his maner was, peeces or counters he had none: yet caſting his hand emptie from him, fly ſayes he, ſhort with a vengeance: then play ſayes he (to his fellow) when in deed there is none but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: but thus with ſuppoſes he playes alone, ſwaggers with his game fellow, out-ſweares him with a thouſand oathes, challenges him the field to anſwer him if he be a man, appoynts the place and all, that if any not knowing his conditions, ſhould ſtand without and heare him, would thinke two ſwaggerers were ſwearing God from heauen.</p>
               <p>To his play againe he falles, ſeuen vp for twelue pence, for that is his game ſtill: well, they fall out, they goe together by the eares, and ſuch a hurley burley is in the roome it paſſes: at the laſt the Stooles they flye about, the Pottes they walke, the Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they go together, nay the Prayer bookes they fly into the fire, that ſuch a noyſe there was, that the whole houſe wondred at his folly, perſwaſions were to no purpoſe, doores would he open none, till they violently brake them open, though they weare of golde, and ſo they did, and entred the Parler, found all this leuell coyle, and his pate broken, his face ſcratcht, and legge out of ioynt, as a
<pb facs="tcp:173897:12"/>
number ſay to this houre, that a is a play fellow for the diuel, and in game they cannot agree: but that is otherwiſe, for in the great Hall, at the ſeruing mens requeſt he will play by himſelfe, if they will not play with him: and who ſo playes with him, though they play for nothing and with nothing, al is one they muſt fall out, and if others be not by to part them, miſchiefe may be done, for he will lay it on, take it off who will: ſo that at his firſt comming hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daungered many, and now take heede is a fayre thing, for few will come neede him. Thus you may ſee fooles that wants wit to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne themſelues well, haue a wilfull will to go forward in folly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How this leane Foole Leanard, eating his belly full, was reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of one that clapt corziars waxe to his head.</head>
               <p>THis leane greedy foole hauing a ſtomacke, and ſeeing the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler out of the way, his appetite was ſuch, as loath to tarrie, breakes open the Dairy houſe, eates and ſpoyles new cheeſe-curdes, cheeſe-cakes, ouerthrowes creame bowles, and hauing fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his belly, and knew he had done euill, gets him gone to <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> in Sherwood, as one fearefull to be at home: the Maydes came home that morning from milking, and finding ſuch a maſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of their Dairie, almoſt mad, thought a yeares wages could not make amends: but O the foole leane <hi>Leanard,</hi> they cryed, hee did this miſchiefe, they complained to their Maſter, but to no purpoſe, <hi>Leanard</hi> was farre enough off, ſearch was made for the foole, but he was gone none knew whither, and it was his propertie hauing done miſchiefe, neuer to come home of himſelfe, but if any one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him, he would eaſily be wonne.</p>
               <p>All this while the foole was at <hi>Mansfield</hi> in Sherwood, &amp; ſtood gaping at a Shoomakers ſtall: who not knowing him, aſked him what he was? go looke ſayes he, I know not my ſelfe: they aſked him where he was borne? at my mothers backe ſaies he: in what countrey quoth they? in the country, quoth he, where God is a good man: at laſt one of the three Iourneymen, imagined hee was not very wiſe, and flouted him very merrily, aſking him if hee would haue a ſtitch where there was a hole? (meaning his mouth) I quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the foole, if your noſe may be the needle: the Shoomaker could haue founde in his hart to haue tooke meaſure on his pate with a
<pb facs="tcp:173897:12"/>
Laſt inſteede of his foote: but let him goe as he was.</p>
               <p>A Countrey Plow Iogger being by, noting al this, ſecretly ſtole a peece of Shoomakers waxe off their ſtall, and comming behinde him, clapt him on the head, &amp; aſked him how he did: the foole ſeeing the pitch ball, pulled to haue it off, but could not but with much paine, in an enuious ſpleene ſmarting ripe, runnes after him, fals at fifty cuffes with him, but the fellowe belaboured the foole cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, and got the fooles head vnder his arme, and bobd his noſe: the foole remembring how his head was, ſtrikes it vp, and hits the fellowes mouth with the pitcht place, ſo that the haire of his head, and the heyre of the clownes beard, were glude together: the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe cryed, the foole exclaimed, and could not ſuddenly part: in the ende the people (after much laughing at the ieſt) let them part faire the one went to picke his beard, the other his head: the Conſtable came, aſkt the cauſe of their falling out, and knowing one to bee <hi>Leanard</hi> the leane Foole, whome he had a warrant from the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to ſearch for, demaundes of the fellowe how it happened? the fellow he could anſwere nothing but vm, vm, for his mouth was ſealed vp with waxe: doeſt thou ſcorne to ſpeake, ſayes hee, I am the Kinges Officer knaue: vm, vm, quoth he againe, meaning he would tell him all when his mouth was cleane: but the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thinking he was mockt, clapt him in the ſtockes, where the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe ſate a long houre farming his mouth: and when hee had done and might tell his griefe, the Conſtable was gone to carry home <hi>Leanard</hi> to his Maiſter, who not at home, he was enforced to ſtay ſupper time, where he tolde the Gentleman the ieſt, who was verie merry to heare the ſtorie, contented the Officer, and bad him to ſet the fellowe at libertie, who betimes in the morning was founde faſt aſleepe in the ſtockes: the fellow knowing himſelfe faultie, put vp his wrongs, quickly departed, and went to worke betimes that morning, with a flea in his eare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:13"/>
               <head>How Leane Leanard eate vp his Maiſters Hawke, and was almoſt choaked with the Fethers.</head>
               <p>THe Gentleman with whom this <hi>Leanard</hi> dwelt, hauing bought a goodly faire Hawke, brought her home, being not a little proud of his penny-worth, and at ſupper to other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, fell a prayſing of her, who ſoothing vp his humor, likewiſe fayled not to ad a toarch of fire to increaſe more flame, for indeede the bird was worthy of commendations, and therefore did merite prayſes. <hi>Leanard</hi> ſtanding by with his finger in his mouth, as it was his cuſtome, often hearing them prayſe the goodneſſe of the Hawke, hought in deed they had meant for goodnes being farre better meate then a Turkey or a Swan, was very deſirous to eate of the ſame: and vnknowne goes downe, and ſodainely from the Pearch ſnatcht the Hawke, and hauing wrong off her necke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to beſiedge that good morſell, but with ſo good a courage, that the fethers had almoſt choakt him: but there lay my friende <hi>Leanard</hi> in a lamentable taking. Well, the Hawke was miſt, and the deed was found, the Maiſter was fetcht, and all men might ſee the Hawke, fethers and all not very well diſgeſted: there was no boote to bid runne for drams to driue downe this vndiſgueſted moddicome: the Gentleman of one ſide, cryed hang the Foole: the Foole on the other ſide cryed not, but made ſignes that his Hawke was not ſo good as he did prayſe her for: and though the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man loued his Hawke, yet he loued the Foole aboue: being enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced rather to laugh at his ſimplicitie, then to vexe at his loſſes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely: Being glad to make himſelfe merry, ieſted on it euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: vpon whoſe Hawke a Gentleman of his, very wiſely writ theſe lynes, and gaue vnto his Maiſter.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Fooles feede without heede, vnhappy be their feeding,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe heed being in ſuch ſpeed, attempted without heeding</l>
                  <l>May they choke that prouoke, appetite by pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>When they eate forbidded meate, and feed ſo out of meaſure.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The Gentleman laught at this rime, yet knew not whether was the more foole: he for writing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other for eating, or he for looſing. Well, putting the Hare to the Gooſe-gibblets, ſeeing there was no remedie, make himſelfe paſtime, pleaſed himſefe, and did reſt contented.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:13"/>
               <head>How the Leane Foole ſet fire on the Wheele-barrow that he loued ſo, vnknowne to himſalfe.</head>
               <p>HEe that miſchiefes many, ſometimes wrongs himſelfe: as har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to this ieſt. <hi>Leanard</hi> of all thinges loued his Wheele-bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, he would worke al day and carry dung in it, yet would ſleepe in it at night: he would ſet vp meate for his belly in it, I what did hee without it? Once at a Chriſtmas time, when the fire in the Hall was full, and <hi>Leanard</hi> was ſore a cold, he got coales out of the Scullery, and put them into his Barrow, and ſet them on fire, and ſo ſate him downe to warme him, quite forgetting it was made of Wood, and Wood would burne: ſo in the ende beeing warme, goes for a Iacke of Beere, bringes it, and ſets it on the fire to warme, ſo that the inſide melted, and hee dranke the drinke notwithſtanding: but on the ſodaine hee ſeeing the Wheele-bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row flame that he ſo loued, aloude he cries O mee, O mee, O mee, and takes it vp flaming, and trundles it into the Hall among the people to ſhew: the young men and maydes tumbled ouer one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other for feare: ſome had their faces burned, others their legges: the maydes their ſmockes, yea one ſet fire on another, for their Aproues burned, and being many people, the flame increaſed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then decreaſed: <hi>Leanard</hi> ſeeing no one would helpe him, runnes (for feare leaſt the Gentleman ſhould know it) and thruſts it into the Barne to hide it, which ſome ſeeing, runnes after, and had they not come at that time, the Hay and Straw had been all burnt, for it was already of a light fire, but being quencht out, all was well: ſuch is the enuie of Fooles, who ſeeing none would helpe him, thought to doe them miſchiefe, which he did, but not much.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <head>A Cleane Foole</head>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:14"/>
               <head>How Iacke Miller ſimply burned the hayre of his head and face.</head>
               <p>IN a Gentlemans houſe where <hi>Iacke Miller</hi> reſorted, as he was welcome to all: it chaunced ſo there was a Play, the Players dreſſed them in the Gentlemans Kitchin, &amp; ſo entred through the Entry into the Hall. It was after dinner when Pyes ſtood in the Ouen to coole for ſupper: <hi>Iacke</hi> had not dyned, and ſeeing the Ouen ſtand open, and ſo many Pyes there vntold (he thought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſeemed numberleſſe) O ſayes <hi>Iacke,</hi> for one of them p. p. pies, for ſo he ſtamered in ſpeking (the Players boy being by, &amp; in his Ladyes Gowne) could haue found in his hart to creepe in clothes and all: but he perſwaded <hi>Iacke</hi> to do ſo, to which he was willing, and very nimbly thruſtes in his head into the hot Ouen, which being but newly opened, on the ſodaine he was ſinged both of head and face, and almoſt not a hayre left on his eye-browes, or beard: <hi>Iacke</hi> cryes, O I burne, and had not the wit to come backe, but lay ſtill: the Gentlewoman boy tooke him by the heeles and pulled him out, but how he looked I wiſh you to iudge that can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne cullours. O <hi>Iacke</hi> was in a bad taking with his face poore ſoule, and lookt ſo vgly, and ſo ſtrangly, that the Lady of the Play being ready to enter before the Gentiles to play her part, no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner began, but remembring <hi>Iacke,</hi> laught out, and could goe no further: the Gentleman inuzed at what he laught: but ſuch a ieſt being eaſily ſeene, was told to the Gentleman, who ſent in for <hi>Iack Miller,</hi> who came like bald Time, to tell them time was paſt of his hayre: but he ſo ſtrangely lookt as his countenance was better then the Play. But againſt night y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Players dreſt them in another place, and at ſupper <hi>Iacke Miller</hi> ſung his ſong of Dirries fayre, with a barmy face to take out the fire, &amp; lookt like the <hi>Pater</hi> of the Alefat it was no boote to bid <hi>Iacke</hi> ſtut &amp; ſtammer, poore foole as cleane as he was, he was now but beaſtly faced, for he looked like a man that being aſham'd to ſhew his face, had hid it in a dry lome wall, and pulling it out againe, left all the hayre behind him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:14"/>
               <head>How the cleane foole was loth to foule his ſhooes, or foule his band.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IAcke,</hi> on Newyéeres day in the morning, was to carry a New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeres gift to a gentleman a myle off; and as he ſtayd to haue it deliuered to him to beare, aſked which was the cleaneſt way thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? A fellow knowing his cleanlineſſe, ſends him ouer a durty marſh: &amp; ſo he folded vp his band (then cleane) for fouling, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at the gentlemans dore he might put it on. The Preſent came, which <hi>Iack</hi> ſéeing, made legs to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, forgetting his band was in his hoſe, caried a ſtif neck to &amp; fro to the gentlewoman, &amp; what ere ſhe ſpake, or where ere ſhe ſtood, <hi>Iack</hi> would look but one way, as though his neck had bin ſtarcht: &amp; remember, ſaies the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, you abuſe not my meſſage, nor my gift. No fo fo forſooth, ſaies <hi>Iack:</hi> and away he goes, &amp; thought he would ſée what it was: &amp; as he went, he lift vp the baſket lid &amp; lookt: Ah ha, quoth <hi>Iack,</hi> I ſée now it is Almond bu bu butter: along he goes, and ſéeing the marſh wet &amp; durty, thought to leape a little ditch, and ſo to goe a cleane hye way: but (O poore <hi>Iack</hi>) he, baſket and all, lay in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the ditch, vp to the arm-pits in mud; which <hi>Iack</hi> ſéeing, gets out, &amp; goes to a riuer by, and waſhes himſelfe firſt, his band next: where, if it had bin about his neck as it ſhould, it had bene labour well ſaued: but laſt his baſket of Almond butter, he waſht y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> durt off ſo long, that the butter was waſht away; which he perceiuing, in that wofull taking comes back, &amp; calles for more bu bu butter. The Gentlewoman ſeeing how things went, rather laught then vext, becauſe ſhee was ſo ſimple to truſt a Foole with matters of truſt, &amp; bade him get in to the fire to dry him, &amp; ſaid, Next time ſhe would ſtay her ſeruants leyſure (who then were abroade) rather then to truſt to a rotten ſtaffe. <hi>Iack</hi> ſtood ſinging Derries faire by the fire, with a Iack of good béere: &amp; while he dryed himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, wet himſelfe within: and there is all the thought hee takes. Thus cleane fooles light ſtill on beaſtly bargaynes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How Iack Miller the cleane foole, ventred ouer the Seuerne on foot in great danger.</head>
               <p>IN the towne of Eſam in Worceſterſh <hi>Iack Miller</hi> being there borne, was much made of in euery place: It hapned that the
<pb facs="tcp:173897:15"/>
Lord Shandoyes Players came to towne, and vſed their paſtime there, which <hi>Iack</hi> not a little loued, eſpecially the Clowne, whom he would imbrace with a ioyfull ſpirit, and call him Grumball (for ſo he called himſelfe in Gentlemens houſes, where he would imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate playes, doing all himſelfe, King, Clowne, Gentleman, and all: hauing ſpoke for one, he would ſuddenly goe in, and agayn re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for the other: and ſtambring ſo beaſtly as he did, made migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty mirth. To conclude, he was a right innocent, without any vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany at all.)</p>
               <p>When theſe Players as I ſpeake of had done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne, they went to Partiar, &amp; <hi>Iacke</hi> ſwore he would goe all the world with Grumball, that he would: it was then a great froſt new begun, &amp; the Hauen was frozen euer thinly: but heere is the wonder, the gentleman y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kept the Hart (an Inne in the town) whoſe backſide looked to the way that led to the riuer ſide to Partiar, lockt vp <hi>Iack</hi> in a chamber next the Hauen, where he might ſée the players paſſe by; and they of the towne loth to loſe his company, deſired to haue it ſo: But he, I ſay, ſéeing them go by, créeps thorow the window, and ſayd, I come to thée, Grumball. The players ſtood all ſtill to ſée further. He got downe very dangerouſly, and makes no more adoe but ventures ouer the Hauen, which is by the long bridge, as I geſſe, ſome forty yards ouer: tut he made nothing of it; but my heart aked to ſée it, and my eares heard the yce crack all the way. When hee was come vnto them, I was amazed, and tooke vp a brickbat (which there lay by) and threw it, which no ſooner fell vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the yce, but it burſt. Was not this ſtrange, that a foole of thirty yeres was borne of that yce, which would not indure the fall of a brickbat? yes, it was wonderfull me thought: but euery one ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him for the déed, telling him it was dangerous. He conſidered his fault, and knowing faultes ſhould bee puniſhed, he intreated Grumball the Clowne, whom hee ſo dearely loued, to whip him; but with Roſemary: for that he thought would not ſmart. But the Players in ieſt bréecht him, till the bloud came, which he tooke laughing: for it was his maner euer to weepe in kindneſſe and laugh in extremes. That this is true, mine eyes were witneſſes, being then by.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:15"/>
               <head>How Iack the cleane foole ſung his ſong of Derries faire in diuers places, where he made good ſport.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IAck Miller</hi> welcomed to all places, and bar'd of none, came to a Gentleman, who being at dinner, requeſted him for mirth, to make him a play, which he did, &amp; to ſing Derries faire, which was in this maner: Firſt, it is to be noted, he ſtutted hugely, and could neyther pronounce b nor p, and thus he began:
<q>
                     <l>As I went to Derries faire, there was I ware of a iolly begger,</l>
                     <l>Miſtris Annis, maſter Thomas, vnder a tree mending of ſhoone,</l>
                     <l>Miſtris Annis, maſter Thomas, hight braue beggers euery one.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo forward: but the ieſt was to heare him pronounce braue beggers: &amp; his quality was, after he began his ſong, no laughing could put him out of it. One ſtanding by, &amp; noting his humour, that b and p plagued him, bade him ſay this after him, which <hi>Iack</hi> ſayd he would doe.</p>
               <p>Buy any flawne, paſties, pudding pies, plumb pottage, or peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cods? O, it was death to <hi>Iack</hi> to do it: but like a willing foole hee fell to it: Buy any, buy any fla flawne, p p p paſties, and p p p pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding p p pies, p p p &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And euer as he hit on the word, he would pat with his finger on his other hand, that more &amp; more it would make a man burſt with laughing, almoſt to ſée his action: ſometime he would be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing one word, while one might go to the dore and come agayne. But euer after, Gentiles would requeſt him to ſpeak that, where before Derries faire was all his ſong.</p>
               <p>He came not long after (to this I am witnes, becauſe my eares heard it) to a Gentlemans not farre from Vpton vpon Seuerne: where at the table (amongſt many gallants and Gentlewomen, almoſt the ſtate of the country) he was to ieſt and ſing, eſpecially they intreated him for his new ſpeach of the pées: which he began in ſuch maner to ſpeake, with driueling and ſtuttering, that they began mightily to laugh: inſomuch that one proper Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man among the reſt, becauſe ſhee would not ſeeme too immodeſt with laughing: for ſuch is the humour of many, that thinke to make all, when God knowes they marre all: ſo ſhe ſtrayning her ſelfe, though inwardly ſhee laughed hartily, gaue out ſuch an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of her modeſty, that all the Table rung on it. Who is that,
<pb facs="tcp:173897:16"/>
ſayes one? Not I, ſaies another: but by her chéeks you might find guilty <hi>Gilberto,</hi> where he had hid the bruſh. This Ieſt made them laugh more, and the rather that ſhe ſtood vpon her marriage, and diſdayned all the gallants there, who ſo hartily laught, that an old gentlewoman at the table tooke ſuch a conceyt at it with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that had not the foole bin, which ſtood (by fortune) at her back, and was her ſupporter, being in a great ſwound, ſhee had fallen to the ground backward: but downe they burſt the windowes for ayre, &amp; there was no little boote to bid runne: ſhe was nine or ten dayes ere ſhe recouered that fit on my knowledge. Thus ſimple <hi>Iack</hi> made mirth to all, made the wiſeſt laugh but to this day ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered little wit to himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <head>A merry Foole</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A deſcription how this merry Foole, being VVill Sommers (the Kings naturall Ieſter) was, as report telles me.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WIll Sommers, borne in Shropſhire, as ſome ſay,</l>
                  <l>Was brought to Greenwitch on a holy day,</l>
                  <l>Preſented to the King, which foole diſdayn'd</l>
                  <l>To ſhake him by the hand; or elſe aſham'd,</l>
                  <l>How e're it was, as ancient people ſay,</l>
                  <l>With much adoe was wonne to it that day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Leane he was, hollow eyde, as all report;</l>
                  <l>And ſtoope he did too, yet in all the Court</l>
                  <l>Few men were more belou'd, then was this foole,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe merry prate kept with the King much rule,</l>
                  <l>When he was ſad, the King and he would rime.</l>
                  <l>Thus Will exiled ſadneſſe many a time.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I could deſcribe him, as I did the reſt;</l>
                  <l>But in my mind I doe not thinke it beſt:</l>
                  <l>My reaſon this, how e're I doe deſcry him,</l>
                  <l>So many knew him, that I may belye him.</l>
                  <l>Therefore to pleaſe all people one by one,</l>
                  <l>I hold it beſt to let that paynes alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173897:16"/>
                  <l>Onely thus much, hee was a poore mans friend,</l>
                  <l>And helpt the widdow often in the end:</l>
                  <l>The King would euer graunt what he did craue;</l>
                  <l>For well he knew Will, no exacting knaue:</l>
                  <l>But wiſht the King to doe good deeds great ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Which cauſde the Court to loue him more and more.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How the merry foole, Will Sommers, brought his vncle to the King, and got him twenty pound a yere.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIll Sommers,</hi> in no little credit in the Kings Court, walking in the Parke at Greene wich, fell a ſléep on the ſtile that leads into the walke, and being many that would haue gone that way, ſo much loued him, that they were loth to diſeaſe him, but went another way, I, the better ſort: but do I make a wonder at that? who ſooner then the better ſort? for now adayes beggers are the gallants, while Gentles of right bloud ſéeme tame Ruffians: but note the loue that <hi>Will Sommers</hi> got: A poore woman ſéeing him ſleep ſo dangerouſly, either to fall backward, or hurt his head lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſo againſt a poſt, fetcht him a cuſhen &amp; a rope; the one for his head, and the other to bind him to the poſt, for falling backward: and thus he ſlept, and the woman ſtood by, attending as groome of his chamber.</p>
               <p>It chanced ſo, that vpon great occaſion, as you ſhal after heare, <hi>Will Sommers</hi> vncle came out of Shropſhire to ſeeke him in the Court: a plaine old man of thréeſcore yeeres, with a buttoned cap, a lockram falling band, courſe, but clean; a ruſſet coat, a white belt of a horſe hide, right horſe-coller whit-leather, a cloſe round bréech of ruſſet ſhéeps wooll, with a long ſtocke of white kerſey, a high ſhooe with yellow buckles, all white with duſt; for that day the good olde man had come thrée and twenty myles on footbacke and horſebacke.</p>
               <p>This kind old man comming vp in his countries behalfe, and comming into Gréenwitch, aſked the way to the Court: euery one directs him: but one villayne Page directs him by the Court gate, to croſſe in a boat ouer to Blackwall, and told him that was the Court. The ſilly old man willingly payd his penny before hand, and was going ouer: but ſome that ouer-heard their talke, hindred
<pb facs="tcp:173897:17"/>
his iourney, and laughed at the ieſt yet pittied his ſimplicity, and ſets him the right way. When he came in and ſaw ſuch a place, he was amazed and ſtood gazing: which the Gard and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women in their windows had much ſport to ſee: at laſt one aſked him what he was?</p>
               <p>The olde man anſwers, A poore Shropſhire man, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds if there were not a Gentleman in the Court dwelling, called by the name of M. <hi>William Sommers?</hi> (for the Countrey hearing him in fauour in the Court, ſayd he was ſo at leaſt.) The Courtier anſwered, Heere is ſuch a one indeed. For fault of a worſe, ſayes he, I am his vncle, &amp; wept with ioy that he ſhould ſée him. Mary, ſaies the man, Ile helpe you to him ſtraight: for I tell you, not any in the Court durſt but haue ſought him, which this man did, and it was told them, hee was walked into the Parke, while the King ſlept that hote day: thither went they to ſeeke him.</p>
               <p>All this while my friend <hi>William</hi> was in counſel with the poſt, and the cuſhen ſtood as arbitrator betwixt them; and the woman by as a witneſſe what was ſayd and done: At laſt, came theſe two &amp; wakened him. <hi>William</hi> feeling his head ſoft, What ſoft poſt is this, quoth he? A poſt of mine owne making, ſayes the woman. But ſhe loſt nothing by her good will: for ere ſhee left <hi>Will Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> ſhe got him to get her ſonnes pardon of the King, who was to he hanged three dayes after for piracy: but by <hi>Will Sommers</hi> meanes he deceyued the hangman. Thus and many good déeds he did to diuers.</p>
               <p>The foole being wakened, looks about him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had thanked the woman, aſked what newes? Saies the man, Sir, here is your vncle come out of the country to ſée you. God a mercy, couſin, ſaies <hi>Will Sommers,</hi> I thank thée for thy labour, you cannot vncle me ſo. Yes truly, ſir, I am your owne deare vncle, M. <hi>William,</hi> and with that wept. Are you my vncle, ſayes <hi>Will?</hi> I ſir, ſayes he. Are you my vncle, ſayes he agayne? I ſure, &amp; verily too. But are you my vncle indéed? By my vowes I am, ſayes the old man. Then vncle, by my vowes, welcome to the Court, ſayes <hi>Will Sommers:</hi> but what make you here vncle? He vp &amp; tels his comming to him. <hi>William</hi> takes him by the hand, come, ſaies he, thou ſhalt ſée <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> vncle, the onely <hi>Harry</hi> in England, and leads him through the Court, through the great Hall, and vp the great Chamber, to the
<pb facs="tcp:173897:17"/>
Chamber of Preſence, and euer and anon cries, Aware, roome for me and my vncle <hi>Williams,</hi> and knaues, bid him welcome. You are welcome, ſir, ſaies one: you are welcom, ſir, ſayes another, that the old man thought himſelfe no earthly man, they honoured him ſo much.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Will</hi> ready to enter the Preſence, lookes on his vncle, and ſéeing him not fine enough to looke on the King: Come vncle, ſaies he, we wil haue this geare mended: leads him to his chamber, and attyres him in his beſt tooles coate, ſimply God wot, meaning well to him, and the ſimple olde man as ſimply put it on, cappe and all.</p>
               <p>Out they come, and vp they came, and to the King they go, who being with the good Lord Treaſurer alone merry, ſéeing them two, how <hi>Will</hi> had got an other foole, knew there was ſport at hand. How now, ſaies the King, what newes with you? O <hi>Harry,</hi> ſayes hee, this is mine owne vncle, bid him welcome, my owne fleſh and bloud. Well, ſayd the King, &amp; he is welcom. <hi>Harry,</hi> ſaies he, heare me tell thee a tale, &amp; I will make thee rich, and my vncle ſhall be made rich by thee. <hi>William</hi> tells the King, how <hi>Terrils Frith</hi> was incloſed. <hi>Terrils Frith,</hi> ſayes the King? what is that? Why, the Heath where I was borne, called by the name of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils Frith:</hi> now a gentleman of that name takes it all in, &amp; makes all the people beleeue it is his; for it tooke the name from him: ſo that, <hi>Harry,</hi> the poore pine, and their cattell are all vndon without thy helpe.</p>
               <p>And what ſhould I do, ſayes the King? Mary, ſayes <hi>William,</hi> ſend to the Biſhop of Hereford, hee is a great man with <hi>Terrill,</hi> commaund him to ſet the <hi>Frith</hi> at liberty agayne, who is now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned by his meanes.</p>
               <p>And how ſhall I be rich by that, ſayes the King? The poore wil pray for thee, ſayes <hi>Will So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mers,</hi> and thou ſhalt be rich in heauen, for on earth thou art rich already. All this was done, &amp; <hi>Williams</hi> vncle went home, who while he liued, for that deed, was allowed Bayly of the Common, and his place was better then twenty pound a yéere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:18"/>
               <head>How this merry foole Will Sommers, to make the King merry, asked him three queſtions.</head>
               <p>HOwſoeuer theſe thrée things came in memory, &amp; are for mirth inſerted into ſtage playes, I know not; but that <hi>Will So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mers</hi> aſked them of the King, it is certayn, there are ſome will affirme it now liuing in Greenwich. The King vpon a time being extreme melancholy and full of paſſion, all that <hi>Will Sommers</hi> could doe, would not make him merry. Ah, ſayes hee, this cloud muſt haue a good ſhowre to clenſe it; &amp; with that goes behind the Arras. <hi>Harry</hi> (ſayes he) Ile go behind the Arras, &amp; ſtudy thée thrée queſtions, and come againe: ſée therefore you lay aſide this melancholy muſe, &amp; ſtudy to anſwer me. I (quoth the King) they will be wiſe ones, no doubt. At laſt, out comes <hi>William</hi> with his wit, as the foole of the play doth with an antick looke, to pleaſe the beholders. <hi>Harry,</hi> ſaies he, what is that the leſſer it is, the more it is to he feared? The K. muſed at it: but to grace the ieſt the better (for he was in that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to grace good will, the excellenteſt Prince on the earth) the King made anſwere, he knew not. <hi>Will</hi> made anſwere, It was a little bridge ouer a déep riuer: at which he ſmilled, knowing it was fearful indéed. What is the next, <hi>William,</hi> ſaies the King? Mary this is next, What is the cleanlieſt trade in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world? Mary, ſayes the King, I think a Comfitmaker: for he deales with nothing but pure ware, &amp; is attyred cleane in white linnen when he ſels it. No <hi>Harry,</hi> ſaies <hi>Will,</hi> you are wide. What ſay you then, qd. the King? Mary, ſaies <hi>Will,</hi> I ſay a durt-dauber. Out on it, ſayes the King, that is the fouleſt; for he is durty vp to the elbowes. I, ſayes <hi>Wil,</hi> but then he waſhes them cleane againe, &amp; eates his meat cleanely enough. I promiſe thée <hi>(Wil)</hi> ſaies the K, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt a prety foolſh wit. I, <hi>Harry,</hi> ſaies he, it wil ſerue to make a wiſer man the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you a foole, me thinks. At this the King laught, &amp; demands the third queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now tell me, ſayes <hi>Will,</hi> if you can, what it is, that being borne without life, head, noſe, lip or eye, and yet runnes terribly roaring through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world till it dies? This is a wonder, qd. the King, &amp; no queſtion, &amp; I know it not. Why, quoth <hi>Wil,</hi> it is a fart. At this the King laught hartily, &amp; was excéeding merry, and bids <hi>Will</hi> aſke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſonable thing, &amp; he would graunt it. Thanks, <hi>Harry,</hi> ſayes he, now againſt I want, I know where to find, for yet I néed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:
<pb facs="tcp:173897:18"/>
but one day I ſhall: for euery man ſées his latter end, but knowe not his beginning. The King vnderſtood his meaning, and ſo pleaſantly departed for that ſeaſon, and <hi>Will</hi> layes him downe amongſt the Spaniels to ſléepe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How Will Sommers the merry foole borrowed ten pounds of Cardinall Wolſey, to pay where the Cardinall owed it.</head>
               <p>ON a time appoynted, the King dyned at Windſor, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell yard, at Cardinall <hi>Wolſeys,</hi> at the ſame time when hee was building y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> admired work of his tombe: at whoſe gate ſtood a number of poore people to be ſerued of almes. When dinner was done within, and as <hi>Wil</hi> paſt by, they ſaluted him, taking him for a worthy perſonage, which pleaſed him.</p>
               <p>In he comes, and finding the King at dinner, and the Cardinal by attending: to diſgrace him that he neuer loued, <hi>Harry,</hi> ſaies he, lend me ten pound. What to do, ſaies the King? To pay thrée or foure of the Cardinals creditors, quoth hee, to whom my word is paſt; and they are come now for their money. That y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt, <hi>Wil,</hi> quoth he. Creditors of mine, ſayes the Cardinall? Ile giue your Grace my head, if any man can iuſtly aſke me a penny. No, ſaies <hi>Will?</hi> lend mee ten pounds, if I pay it not where thou oweſt it, Ile giue thée twenty for it. Doe ſo, ſaies the King. That I wil, my Liege, ſaies the Cardinal, though I know I owe none. With that he lends <hi>Wil Sommers</hi> ten pound. <hi>Will</hi> goes to the gate, and diſtributes it to the poore, and brought the empty bag: there is thy bag againe, ſayes he, and thy creditors are ſatiſfied, and my word out of danger.</p>
               <p>Who receyued it, ſayes the King? the Brewer, or the Baker? Neyther <hi>(Harry)</hi> ſayes <hi>Will Sommers:</hi> But (Cardinal) anſwere me in one thing: To whom doeſt thou owe thy ſoule? To God (quoth he.) To whom thy wealth? To the poore, ſaies he. Take thy forfet <hi>(Harry)</hi> ſayes the foole, open confeſſion, ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> penance: his head is thine; for to the poore at the gate I payd his debt, which he yéelds is due: or if thy ſtony heart wil not yéeld it ſo, ſaue thy head by denying thy word, &amp; lend it me: thou knoweſt I am poore, and haue neither wealth nor wit, &amp; what thou lendeſt to the poore, God wil pay thée ten fold: he is my ſurety, arreſt him; for by my troth
<pb facs="tcp:173897:19"/>
hang me when I pay thée. The King laught at the ieſt, and ſo did the Cardinall for a ſhew, but it grieued him to ieſt away ten pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo: yet worſe tricks then this <hi>Will Sommers</hi> ſerued him after; for indéed he could neuer abide him; and the forfeiture of his head had like to haue bene payd, had he not poyſoned himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How this merry Foole Will Sommers eate a meſſe of Milke without a ſpoone.</head>
               <p>THere was in the time of <hi>Will Sommers,</hi> an other artificiall Ieſter or foole in the Court, whoſe ſubtilty heapt vp wealth in rewards &amp; gifts giuen him, which <hi>Wil Sommers</hi> could neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide him for: but indeed, lightly one foole cannot indure the ſight of another, as <hi>Iacke Oates</hi> did the Minſtrell in the flat fooles ſtory; and one begger is wo, another by the dore ſhould goe.</p>
               <p>This Ieſter was a byg man of a great voyce, long black locks, and a very big round beard. On a time (of purpoſe) <hi>Will Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> watcht to diſgrace him, when hee was iuggling and ieſting before the King. <hi>Will Sommers</hi> brings vp a meſſe of milk and a manchet: <hi>Harry</hi> (ſayes he) lend me a ſpoone. Foole, ſayes the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, vſe thy hand: help hands, I haue no lands; &amp; meanes that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would warrant his groſſe féeding. I, ſayes <hi>Will Sommers,</hi> beaſts will féede ſo, and beaſts will bid other doe, as they will doe themſelues. <hi>Will,</hi> ſayes the King, thou knoweſt I haue none. True, <hi>Harry</hi> (ſayes he) I know that, therefore I aſke thée: and I would (but for doing thée harme) thou hadſt no tongue to graunt that foole his next ſute: but I muſt eat my creame ſome way. The King, the Ieſter, and all gathers about him to ſée him eat it. <hi>Wil</hi> begins thus to ryme ouer his milke:
<q>
                     <l>This bit, Harry, I giue to thee, and this next bit muſt ſerue for me,</l>
                     <l>Both which Ile eat apace.</l>
                     <l>This bit (Madam) vnto you, and this bit I my ſelfe eat now,</l>
                     <l>And all the reſt vpon thy face,</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Meaning the foole, in whoſe beard &amp; head the bread and milk was thick ſown, &amp; his eyes almoſt put out. <hi>Wil Sommers</hi> he gets him gone for feare. This luſty Ieſter forgetting himſelfe, in fury drawes his dagger, &amp; begins to proteſt. Nay, ſaies the King, are ye ſo hote, clap him faſt: and though he drawes his dagger here, yet
<pb facs="tcp:173897:19"/>
let him put it vp in another place. The poore abuſed Ieſter was ieſted out of countenance, &amp; lay in durance a great while, till <hi>Wil Sommers</hi> was fayne to (after he had broke his head, to giue him a playſter) get him out agayne: but neuer after came my Iuggler in the Court more, ſo néere the King, being ſuch a dangerous man to draw in the preſence of.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <head>A very Foole</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> How Iohn of the Hoſpitall, the very foole, walkt and preacht in Paules Church, and was bidden to dinner.</head>
               <p>THis innocent Ideot, that neuer harmed any, before I enter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further, I will let you vnderſtand in two words, how hee came to be of the Hoſpitall of Chriſts Church: Some certayne yeres ſince (but not a few yeres) there dwelt a poore blind woman in Bow lane in London, called by the name of blind <hi>Alice,</hi> who had this foole of a child to lead her, in whoſe houſe he would ſit, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the ſtaires, or in a corner, &amp; ſing Pſalmes, or preach to him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> becauſe hee delighted to goe to Sermons with blind <hi>Alice,</hi> &amp; heard the Preacher talke of them. It chanced the Worſhipful of the City (good Benefactors to the poore) to take her into Chriſtes Hoſpitall, with whome <hi>Iohn</hi> went as a guide to lead her; who being olde, after ſhe dyed, he was to be turned out of doore: but the City more deſirous to pity, then to be cruell, placed him as a foſtered fatherleſſe chylde; and they did well in it too, ſeeing hee was one of Gods creatures, though ſome difference in perſons.</p>
               <p>Well, to go forward in what I promiſed you: <hi>Iohn</hi> went to S. <hi>Paules</hi> Church in London, to méete with M. <hi>Nowel</hi> the Deane, whoſe bounty to him was great, &amp; the toole knew it well ynough, whom he would duely attend after his preaching; for euer he gaue him at their méeting a groat, and he would bring it to his Nurſe: Well, M. Deane preached not that day: whereupon <hi>Iohn</hi> ſtands in a corner with boyes flocking about him, and begins to preach himſelfe, holding vp his muckender for his booke, and reades his text.</p>
               <p>It is written (ſayes he) in the 3. chapter of <hi>Paul</hi> to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,
<pb facs="tcp:173897:20"/>
Brethren, you muſt not ſweare (for that was lightly al his text) then thus he begins: Whereas, or whereunto it is written: for becauſe you muſt beléeue it: for ſurely elſe we are no Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Write y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſermon (boy) ſayes he (as the Hoſpital boyes do:) &amp; then one muſt write on his hand, with his finger, and then hee would go forward thus: The world is proud, and God is angry if we do not repent. Good friend giue me a pin, or good friend giue mée a poynt, as it came in his mind: and ſo ſucking vp his driuell and breath together, would pray and make an end: which being done, who bids me home to dinner now, ſaies <hi>Iohn?</hi> The boyes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knew his qualities, anſwers, that do I, <hi>Iohn.</hi> Thank ye (friend) ſayes he, &amp; goes home to his owne dwelling at Chriſts Church. But at this time one wealthy Marchants ſon, to make his father merry, bade him home to dinner indéed, &amp; will be, or nill he, he muſt goe with him: with much ado <hi>Iohn</hi> went, &amp; comming into the houſe, ſimply ſits him downe (as his vſe was) in the chimney corner. It was in Lent, when peaſe pottage bare great ſway, &amp; when euery peaſe muſt haue his eaſe. <hi>Iohn</hi> beholding peaſe pottage on the fire, thoughr on his Nurſe; for he was all ſauing for her: &amp; when the roome was empty, forgetting what his pocket was made of, thogh of leather, yet not ſufficient; but a good helpe from further harme, as you ſhall heare: he ſéeing no body by, ſtopt to the pot, and put a great ladle of pottage into his pocket, and pittiouſly burnt his thigh; and but that the leather was thick, it had bin worſe: for if it had bene Canuas, it had ſpoyled all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> féeling ſomething burne, leapt and cryed: they ran in to ſée the matter why he cryed, but more &amp; more he exclaimed, I burn I burne, &amp; got out of doores, and neuer leaues till he came to his Nurſe, who quickly ſhifted him, &amp; mended what was amiſſe. But the ieſt was to ſée the folks of the houſe, who wondring what he ayled, could not deuiſe what the matter was: but a begger in the entry, who beheld all, told the truth of the matter, who loſt a good almes for his labour. But thus ſimple <hi>Iohn</hi> by his owne folly, dyed the inſide of his pocket, peaſe pottage tawny, and ſet a good ſcarlet red vpon his thigh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:20"/>
               <head>How Iohn towled the Bell for his Nurſes Chicken.</head>
               <p>GAffer <hi>Homes</hi> being Sexton of Chriſts Church, would often ſet <hi>Iohn</hi> a worke, to towle the bell to prayers or burials, wherin he delighted much: it chaunced ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> comming through the church, and hauing nothing to do, ſéeing the bel ſo eaſy to come by, towles it. The people (as the cuſtome is) repaires to church (as they vſed) to know for whom it was. <hi>Iohn</hi> anſwers them ſtil, For his Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes chicken. They ſayd, Wherefore towles the bell, <hi>Iohn?</hi> I know not. When dyed hee? Euen now. Who, <hi>Iohn?</hi> who? My Nurſes chicken, quoth he, and laughes. This ieſt was known to euery neighbour thereabouts, who ſent to bid him leaue towling: but it was not his cuſtome, till good man <hi>Homes</hi> tooke the rope from him, that gaue the rope to him: though goodma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Homes</hi> gaue him one rope, he had forgotten that <hi>Iacks</hi> wit was not ſo good, to remember any thing.</p>
               <p>Well, there ſtood <hi>Iacke</hi> towling from foure a clock to ſix, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Homes</hi> being from home, who was not a little vext at <hi>Iohns</hi> diligence: but he layd the rope euer after, where <hi>Iohn</hi> could not reach it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How this very foole Iohn of the Hoſpital, ſold a gentlemans paire of boots for a groat, that coſt the Cobler fiue ſhillings.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IOhn</hi> was of this humour, aſke him what his coate coſt him, he would ſay a groate: what his cap, band or ſhirt coſt, all was a groat: aſke what his beard coſt, and ſtill a groat: So one Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day morning there was a Gentleman to ride downe into War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wickſhire, about payment of twenty pound vpon a bonds for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyture: the time was next day by Sunne ſet, it was no boote to bid him pull on his bootes and be gone. Well, he made haſte, and went to do it without bidding too, &amp; yet for all his haſte, his boots were ſeame-rent, and muſt haue a ſtitch or two néedes: he ſends them to a Cobler, next to Chriſts Church gate in Newgate mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, who was diligent to mend them ſtraight: and as he had done, comes <hi>Iohn</hi> of the Hoſpital to him (as his vſe was) to carry home his worke, and he ſends <hi>Iohn</hi> home with the boots: As <hi>Iohn</hi> was
<pb facs="tcp:173897:21"/>
going through Iuy lane, a Countrey fellow that knew him not, méets him, and ſéeing the boots, What ſhall I giue thée for them, ſayes he? <hi>Iohn</hi> (who ſold euery thing for a groate) aſked a groate, The fellow turnes them &amp; winds them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that reaſonable price, and ſeeing it was a good pennyworth, giues him a groat ſuddenly, and departs with the boots. <hi>Iohn,</hi> who vſed to take a great of M. Deane, and would carry it to his Nurſe, did ſo now with his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. She aſked him where he had it? He ſayd, For boots: but ſhee not knowing his mind, forgot the ieſt, and tell to worke againe as he found her.</p>
               <p>The forfeiture of twenty pound ſo hammered in this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans head, that he thought euery houre two, till he had his boots, and muſed they came not from me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, ſends for them preſently. One comes ſweating, zoones (Cobler) the boots; &amp; being at worke very buſy, I, ſayes he, they are mended and caryed home. Another comes, Boots, boots. Would the boots were in your belly, quoth the Cobler, once againe they are gone home. By &amp; by comes the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in his white linnen boot-hoſe ready to the purpoſe. A poxe of lazy Coblers, ſaies hee, my boots; ſhall I forfet a bond for your pleaſure? The Cobler puts off his conſidering rap, why ſir, ſayes he, I ſent them home but now. By whome, ſayes he? By <hi>Iohn,</hi> blew <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſayes the Cobler. The gentleman he runs home one way, the Cobler he another way: wel, no boots were to be had: the gentleman he ſtayed, and the Cobler he prayed; but all this while the boots delayd and came not.</p>
               <p>The Cobler ſéeks <hi>Iohn</hi> at his Nurſes, thinking he forgot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and went home? wel, true it was, &amp; there he was indéed, who after the matter was examined, the boots were knowne to be ſold by <hi>Iohn</hi> for a groat. The Cobler ſéeing no remedy, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was in haſte, giues him fiue ſhillings with a heauy hey he, and loſt foure ſhillings eyght pence by the bargayne: but the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler would neuer let <hi>Iohn</hi> carry home his ware more: nay, ſayes the Cobler, if my mony can be booted and ride poſt it by fiue ſhillings at a time, it is no boote for me to ſay. <hi>Vtinam:</hi> but the next bootes Ile make a page of my owne age, and carry home my ſelfe: for I ſée fooles will afford good pennyworthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:173897:21"/>
               <head>How this very foole Iohn, loſt himſelfe on Eaſter Munday at the Spittle Sermon, amongſt all the people.</head>
               <p>ON Eaſter Munday the auncient cuſtome is, that all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Hoſpitall goe before my Lord Maior to the Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, that the world may witneſſe the workes of God and man, in maintenance of ſo many poore people, the better to ſtirre vp liuing mens mindes to the like good, if God ſhould call them: amongſt which, the children of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hoſpitall leads on; before whom, as chief Captayn, goes <hi>Iohn;</hi> whom to behold the people flock apace, and the weather being hote, their thruſting made <hi>Iohn</hi> in ſuch a hote temper, that he was extreme dry. <hi>Iohn</hi> conſidering he was like to faſt till dinner, yet kéeps on his ranke till he came to the Spittle, where the cannes did walke apace by his noſe, but neuer came at him, which made him the more eager of drink. Well, while the children were placing, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſtood to make water, &amp; ſéeing a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans dore open, ſlips in, and the houſhold without, ſtanding to ſée my Lord Maior paſſe by, not regarded him: but he, whole noſe had wit to ſmell good beere, got downe into the Seller, &amp; fell to it tipple ſquare, till he was loſt and quite drunke, &amp; layd himſelfe to ſléepe behind two barrels; &amp; vnſeene ſlept all that day. In the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon time he was miſt, ſought and not found, inquired after, but he was a more foole that ſought the foole. The afternoone came, the gentlemans Butler with other good fellowes fell to carrouſe ſoundly, till the Butler was layd vp too: heere was a Seller wel fraught with fooles: but all this while the Beadles fayled not to ſearch vp &amp; downe the city; yea, the cryer cryed a man child of the age of two &amp; thirty yeres; for at leaſt he was ſo olde, yet one ſaies he had not wit enough to looke to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>But returne we to the Seller: the two drunkards wak't both together. <hi>Iohn</hi> he calls, Nurſe, Nurſe: which the Butler (halfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake) hearing, thought the deuill had bin playing bo péepe with him: but when he looked &amp; beheld him, he was amazed at it, imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining how it was, and ſo ſecretly ſent him to the Hoſpital, leſt he were blamed for his negligence in looking to the dore no better the day before.</p>
               <p>A number of things more <hi>Iohn</hi> did, which I omit, fearing to
<pb facs="tcp:173897:22"/>
be tedious: not long after he dyed, and was old; for his beard was full of white haires, as his picture in Chriſts Hoſpitall (now to be ſéene) can witneſſe: buryed he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is, but with no Epitaph. Mee thinks, thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in his life time could afford him his picture, might with his graue yéeld ſo much as foure lyues, that people may ſee where he lyes, whom they ſo wel knew: and if I might perſwade, his Motto ſhould be thus, and to this effect:
<q>
                     <l>Heere vnder ſleepes blew Iohn, that giues</l>
                     <l>Food to feede wormes, yet he not liues:</l>
                     <l>You that paſſe by, looke at his graue,</l>
                     <l>And ſay, your ſelues the like muſt haue.</l>
                     <l>Wiſe men and fooles all one end makes:</l>
                     <l>Gods will be done, who giues and takes.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus (Gentlemen) as the kinde Hoſteſſe ſalutes her gheſtes, ſaying, You ſée your cheere, and you are welcome: Euen to ſay I, deſiring that you will pardon my folly, in writing of folly: which folly can no way be excuſed but by your fauour: ſo as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſayd, <hi>Veni, vidi, vici:</hi> I am bolde to buſie your brayne with any darke <hi>Enigma.</hi> Wherfore if my pardon may be purchaſed, then ſo: if not, the worſt is, you will ſay the Authour may kéepe his ſixe fooles company.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:173897:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
